People back home call me a heckler,
الناس يدعونني بالمقاطع
a troublemaker, an irritant,
محب للمشاكل ومزعج
a rebel, an activist,
متمرد وناشط
the voice of the people.
صوت الناس .
But that wasn't always me.
ولكني لم اكن هكذا دائماً .
Growing up, I had a nickname.
وأنا صغير ، كان لدي لقب .
They used to call me Softy,
لقد أعتاد الناس أن ينادوني سوفتي ،
meaning the soft, harmless boy.
وهذه الكلمه تعني ، ولد غير مؤذ .
Like every other human being, I avoided trouble.
وكحال الكثيرين من الناس ، فقد كنت أتجنب المشاكل .
In my childhood, they taught me silence.
في فترة طفولتي ، علموني الصمت .
Don't argue, do as you're told.
لا تجادل ، وقم بما يوكل إليك .
In Sunday school, they taught me don't confront, don't argue,
وفي أيام المدرسة ، علموني بأن لا أواجه ، ولا أجادل ،
even if you're right, turn the other cheek.
وحتى لو كنت على حق ، أدر لخصمك خدك الأخر .
This was reinforced by the political climate of the time.
وهذا تم تعزيزه من قبل المناخ السياسي في ذلك الوقت
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
Kenya is a country where you are guilty
كينيا هي بلد تعتبر فيها مذنباً
until proven rich.
حتى تثبت أنك غني
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
Kenya's poor are five times more likely
فقراء كينيا من المحتمل 5 مرات أكثر
to be shot dead by the police who are meant to protect them
أن يقتلوا من الشرطة التي من المفترض أن تحميهم
than by criminals.
أكثر من إحتمال قتلهم من المجرمين .
This was reinforced by the political climate of the day.
وهذا تم تعزيزه عبر المناخ السياسي في ذلك الوقت
We had a president, Moi, who was a dictator.
لقد كان لدينا رئيس ، إسمه موي وكان ديكتاتوراً
He ruled the country with an iron fist,
لقد حكم البلاد بقبضه من حديد
and anyone who dared question his authority
وأي شخص يتجرأ ويعترض على السلطة
was arrested, tortured, jailed or even killed.
كان يتم إعتقاله ، تعذيبه سجنه ، أو حتى قتله
That meant that people were taught to be smart cowards, stay out of trouble.
وهذا يعني أن الناس تعلموا بأن يكونوا جبناء أذكياء بدلاً من المشاكل
Being a coward was not an insult.
فكونك جبان هذه لا تعني إهانة .
Being a coward was a compliment.
بل تعني مدحاً .
We used to be told that a coward goes home to his mother.
لقد إعتدنا أن نسمع بأن الجبان يرجع إلى البيت ويرى أمه .
What that meant: that if you stayed out of trouble you're going to stay alive.
وهذا يعني : أنك إذا ابتعدت عن المشاكل فستبقى على قيد الحياة .
I used to question this advice,
لقد إعتدت على مثل هذه النصائح ،
and eight years ago we had an election in Kenya,
وقبل 8 سنوات جرت إنتخابات في كينيا
and the results were violently disputed.
وكانت النتيجة إنقسام عنيف
What followed that election was terrible violence, rape,
وقد تبع هذه الإنتخابات العنف الشديد ، والإغتصاب ،
and the killing of over 1,000 people.
ومقتل أكثر من 1,000 شخص .
My work was to document the violence.
وكان عملي هو أن أقوم بتوثيق مشاهد العنف
As a photographer, I took thousands of images,
وكمصور ، فقد التقطت آلاف الصور،
and after two months,
وبعد شهرين ،
the two politicians came together, had a cup of tea,
اجتمع السياسيان، وأحتسوا كوبا من الشاي،
signed a peace agreement, and the country moved on.
وقعوا على معاهدة سلام، ومضت الأمور.
I was a very disturbed man because I saw the violence firsthand.
لقد كنت منزعجا جدا، لإني رأيت العنف بأم عيني .
I saw the killings. I saw the displacement.
رأيت القتل ورأيت النزوح .
I met women who had been raped, and it disturbed me,
لقد قابلت إحدى النساء اللواتي أغتصبن وقد أزعجتني قصتها ،
but the country never spoke about it.
ولكن البلد لم تنشغل بقصتها أبداً .
We pretended. We all became smart cowards.
لقد تصنعنا. بأننا جميعاً جبناء أذكياء .
We decided to stay out of trouble and not talk about it.
وقررنا أن نبقى أنفسنا بعيداً عن المشاكل وان لا نتكلم عنها
Ten months later, I quit my job. I said I could not stand it anymore.
وبعد 10 أشهر ، تركت عملي . وقلت لنفسي بأني لن أحتمل ذلك بعد.
After quitting my job, I decided to organize my friends
وبعد تركي لعملي ، قررت بأن أنظم أصدقائي
to speak about the violence in the country,
وأن نتكلم عن العنف الموجود في البلد ،
to speak about the state of the nation,
أن نتكلم عن حالة الأمة ،
and June 1, 2009 was the day that we were meant to go to the stadium
وكان يوم 1 يونيو لعام 2009 هو اليوم الذي اتفقنا فيه بالذهاب للملعب
and try and get the president's attention.
وأن نحاول جلب إنتباه الرئيس .
It's a national holiday,
وكان يوم عطلة وطنية ،
it's broadcast across the country,
وكان الخطاب يبث عبر البلاد ،
and I showed up at the stadium.
فحضرت في الملعب .
My friends did not show up.
ولكن أصدقائي لم يحضروا .
I found myself alone,
لقد وجدت نفسي وحيدا ،
and I didn't know what to do.
ولم أعلم حينها ما يجب فعله .
I was scared,
لقد كنت خائفاً ،
but I knew very well that that particular day,
ولكنني كنت أعلم جيداً بأن هذا اليوم بالتحديد
I had to make a decision.
يجب أن أتخذ قراراً .
Was I able to live as a coward, like everyone else,
هل سأبقى أعيش جباناً ، مثل البقية
or was I going to make a stand?
أو يجب علي أن أقوم بتغير ؟
And when the president stood up to speak,
وعندما قام الرئيس ليلقي خطابه ،
I found myself on my feet shouting at the president,
وجدت نفسي واقفاً وأصرخ بوجهه ،
telling him to remember the post-election violence victims,
مخبراً إياه بأن يتذكر ضحايا العنف الذين سقطوا بعد الإنتخابات ،
to stop the corruption.
وأن يوقف الفساد .
And suddenly, out of nowhere,
وفجأةً ، وبدون سابق إنذار
the police pounced on me like hungry lions.
أمسكتني الشرطة ، تماماً كالأسد الجائع .
They held my mouth
لقد كمموا فمي
and dragged me out of the stadium,
وجروني خارج الملعب
where they thoroughly beat me up and locked me up in jail.
وأشبعوني ضرباً وزجوني بالسجن
I spent that night in a cold cement floor in the jail,
لقد أمضيت تلك الليلة على أرضية السجن الباردة ،
and that got me thinking.
وهذا جعلني أفكر .
What was making me feel this way?
ما الذي دفعني للقيام بذلك ؟
My friends and family thought I was crazy because of what I did,
إعتقد أصدقائي وعائلتي بأني مجنون بسبب ما قمت بعمله ،
and the images that I took were disturbing my life.
والصور التي التقطها كانت تعكّر حياتي .
The images that I took were just a number to many Kenyans.
والصور التي التقطها كانت فقط للعديد من الكينين ،
Most Kenyans did not see the violence.
معظم الكينين لم يروا العنف .
It was a story to them.
فكانت هذه قصة بالنسبه لهم .
And so I decided to actually start a street exhibition
ولذا قررت أن أبدأ بمعرض في الشارع
to show the images of the violence across the country
لأعرض مشاهد العنف عبر البلاد
and get people talking about it.
وأجعل الناس يتحدثون عنها .
We traveled the country and showed the images,
لقد تنقلنا عبر البلاد ، وعرضنا هذه الصور
and this was a journey that has started me to the activist path,
وهذه كانت بداية رحلتي للعمل كناشط
where I decided to become silent no more,
وأن أخرج عن صمتي للأبد
to talk about those things.
وأن أتكلم عن هذه الأشياء
We traveled, and our general site from our street exhibit
لقد تنقلنا ، وأصبح موقعنا العام من المعرض المقام بالشارع
became for political graffiti about the situation in the country,
مكاناً للشعارات السياسية وعن الأوضاع في البلد
talking about corruption, bad leadership.
عن الفساد ، وعن القيادة السيئة .
We have even done symbolic burials.
لقد قمنا حتى بمدافن رمزية .
We have delivered live pigs to Kenya's parliament
لقد قمنا بإيصال خنازير حية إلى البرلمان الكيني
as a symbol of our politicians' greed.
كرمز على جشع السياسين .
It has been done in Uganda and other countries,
لقد حصل مثل ذلك في اوغندا ، وبلدان أخرى
and what is most powerful is that the images have been picked by the media
وأقوى شيء هو أن ذلك تم تصويره من قبل الاعلام
and amplified across the country, across the continent.
وتم تناقله عبر البلد ، لا بل وعبر القارة .
Where I used to stand up alone seven years ago,
وحيث كنت أقف وحيداً قبل 7 أعوام
now I belong to a community of many people who stand up with me.
الان أصبحت أنتمي إلى مجتمع من أناس كثر يقفون بجانبي
I am no longer alone when I stand up to speak about these things.
لم أعد وحيداً ابداً ، عندما أتكلم عن هذه الاشياء .
I belong to a group of young people who are passionate about the country,
إنني أنتمي إلى مجموعة الشباب الذين يعشقون الوطن
who want to bring about change,
ويريدون أن يحدثوا تغيراً
and they're no longer afraid, and they're no longer smart cowards.
ولم يعودوا خائفين أبداً، ولم يعودوا جبناء أذكياء.
So that was my story.
وهذه هي قصتي .
That day in the stadium,
ذلك اليوم في الملعب،
I stood up as a smart coward.
الذي وقفت فيه كجبان ذكي .
By that one action, I said goodbye to the 24 years living as a coward.
بهذا الحدث ، قلت وداعاً ل 24 سنة من العيش كجبان .
There are two most powerful days in your life:
هنالك يومين قويين في حياتك :
the day you're born, and the day you discover why.
اليوم الذي تولد فيه ، واليوم الذي تكتشف فيه لماذا .
That day standing up in that stadium shouting at the President,
ذلك اليوم الذي وقفت فيه بالملعب صارخاً بوجه الرئيس
I discovered why I was truly born,
اكتشفت فيه ما الغاية من ولادتي
that I would no longer be silent in the face of injustice.
وأني لن أعود إلى صمتي أبداً في وجه الظلم .
Do you know why you were born?
هل تعلمون لماذا ولدتم ؟
Thank you.
شكرا .
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
Tom Rielly: It's an amazing story.
توم رايلي: إنها قصة مذهلة.
I just want to ask you a couple quick questions.
أريد فقط أن أسئلك سؤالين سريعين
So PAWA254:
اذاً : PAWA254
you've created a studio, a place where young people can go
لقد قمت بإنشاء مكان يجتمع فيه الشباب
and harness the power of digital media
تسخرون فيه قوة الإعلام الرقمي
to do some of this action.
للقيام ببعض الأحداث .
What's happening now with PAWA?
ماذا حصل الان بمجموعة PAWA ؟
Boniface Mwangi: So we have this community of filmmakers,
بونيفاس موانغي: لدينا هذا المجتمع من السينمائيين
graffiti artists, musicians, and when there's an issue in the country,
فنانين لكتابة الشعارت ، موسيقيين ، وعندما يكون هناك حدث في البلد
we come together, we brainstorm, and take up on that issue.
نجتمع مع بعضنا ونفكر بعمق بخصوص هذه القضية .
So our most powerful tool is art,
لذا فإن أقوى سلاح لدينا هو الفن
because we live in a very busy world where people are so busy in their life,
لأننا نعيش في عالم مشغول جداً حيث الناس مشغولين بحياتهم
and they don't have time to read.
وليس لديهم وقت للقراءة .
So we package our activism and we package our message in art.
لذلك نجمع أنشطتنا ورسائلنا على شكل فني
So from the music, the graffiti, the art, that's what we do.
وهكذا من خلال الكتابة ، والفن ، هذا ما نفعله
Can I say one more thing?
هل يمكنني أن أقول شيئاً أخر ؟
TR: Yeah, of course. (Applause)
توم :بالطبع .(تصفيق )
BM: In spite of being arrested, beaten up, threatened,
بونيفاس : بالرغم من أنه تم إعتقالي ، وضربي ، وتهديدي
the moment I discovered my voice,
ولكن في اللحظة التي إكتشفت فيها نفسي
that I could actually stand up for what I really believed in,
وأني بإمكاني الوقوف فعلياً للشيء الذي أؤمن به
I'm no longer afraid.
لم أعد خائفاً .
I used to be called softy, but I'm no longer softy,
لقد كنت أدعى باللطيف ولكنني لم أعد كذلك أبداً
because I discovered who I really am, as in, that's what I want to do,
لإنني إكتشفت من أنا بالفعل ، وما الذي أود القيام به
and there's such beauty in doing that.
وهناك شيء جميل للقيام بذلك .
There's nothing as powerful as that, knowing that I'm meant to do this,
ليس هنالك شيء أقوى من ذلك وهو أن تعرف بأنك قصدت هذا
because you don't get scared, you just continue living your life.
وذلك لأنك لم تعد خائفاً ، واستمرت حياتك
Thank you.
شكراً .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)